本剧改编自圣经  它们曾改变世界
本剧将始终保持《圣经》真谛
《圣经》前情提要
Previously on the Bible...
人类的败坏引发了洪水
Human failings led to the great flood.
错误的选择  错误的决定
Wrong choices, wrong decisions.
诺厄之后  上主更新了世界
After Noah, a new beginning...
而且天主给亚巴郎一个许诺
And a promise for Abraham.
天主同我说话了
God has spoken to me.
他将指引我们去新的家园
He will lead us to a new home.
他保证我的后裔会多如繁星
He has promised descendants as numerous as the stars.
为帮助以色列人实现允诺
To help the Israelites fulfill the promise,
天主派梅瑟解救他们  摆脱奴役
God sent Moses to free them from slavery.
主啊
Lord!
若苏厄带领他们进入了盟约之地
Joshua led them into the promised land.
耶利哥是我们的
Jericho is ours!
以色列  以色列
Israel! Israel!
然而以色列人遭遇了培肋舍特人
But the Israelites faced brutal opposition...
残暴的对待
from the Philistines.
有些人敢于斗争反抗
Some dared to fight back.
但即使是三松也没能战胜他们
But not even Samson could overcome them.
先知撒慕尔以天主之名指引以色列人
The prophet Samuel led the Israelites in God's name,
可人们并不满足
But the people wanted more--
他们想要一个能带他们冲锋陷阵的人
someone to lead them in battle.
-你们想要什么  -一位国王
- What do you want? - A King.
国王
A king?
他们会变成暴君
They become tyrants.
由天主选中的国王不会这样
Not if they are chosen by God.
撒乌尔 我傅你作以色列第一任王
Saul, I anoint you the first king of Israel.
愿我作为天主的先知  尽己所能辅佐你
May I, as God's prophet, help you in any way I can.
然而真的有人够格统治神的国度吗
But is any man good enough to rule God's kingdom?
圣经
将士们都准备好了吗
Are the men ready?
都准备好了
They're ready.
撒慕尔在哪里
Where is Samuel?
他应该在这儿的
He should be here.
出击之前  我们必须举行祭祀
We must make a sacrifice before we attack.
我们不能再等了
We cannot wait any longer.
撒乌尔 愿天主宽恕你
Saul! May God forgive you!
撒慕尔
Samuel.
你去哪儿了
Where were you?
我们等了你七天
Seven days we have waited.
足足七天
Seven days.
战士们都离我而去了
My men are deserting.
那就担起国王的责任来
Then be a king.
把司祭的工作交给我
Leave the job of priest to me.
你觉得比起我  天主会更看重你的祭祀吗
Do you think God values your sacrifice more than mine?
撒慕尔
Samuel.
天主命令你们  人畜一个不留
God instructs you: kill everyone and everything.
感谢YYETS字幕组
原始翻译时间轴及制作
天主教长沙青年团体重制
本字幕采用天主教思高译本
仅供福传学习
禁止用于任何商业盈利行为
以色列史上的一个新时代开始了
A new era in Israelite history is beginning--
先知与国王的时代
The period of prophets and kings.
他们必须齐心协力
They must work together
保卫盟约之地
to secure the promised land.
胜利
Victory!
撒乌尔 撒乌尔
Saul! Saul!
天主与我同在
God is with me!
你只有一项任务  上主的一道简单的旨意
You had one task! One simple command from God!
-摧毁一切  -我们已遵从了他的命令
- Destroy everything! - We followed his commands.
那我听到的这些羊叫声是怎么回事
Then what is this bleating of goats in my ears?
又怎么会有牛群的低哞和羊羔的哀叫
What is this lowing of cattle and wailing of lambs?
死的东西会哭吗
Can the dead cry out?
这个异教徒国王又是谁
And who is this pagan King?
过会儿就处死他
He is to be put to death later.
主说宽恕  你便宽恕
When the Lord says spare, you spare.
-主说杀  -撒慕尔
- When he says kill... - Samuel!
你是我们的先知  但我是你的国王
You are our Prophet, but I am your King!
天主的恩宠随时可以收回
What the Lord gives he can take away.
这是天主说的还是你说的
Are these God's words or yours?
你的后裔本可以统治逾千年
Your descendants could have ruled for over a thousand years.
但今天
But today...
天主已经放弃你了
God has forsaken you.
天主还说了什么
More divine words?
天主已收回你的能力
God has torn your power from you.
他要找一个合他心意的人
He wants a man after his own heart.
如果你想为天主教的影视字幕出一份福传的力量， 请来Q群180574695【天主的译站】指导交流!
-给我倒酒  -陛下
- Bring me wine. - Sire.
-听到没有  快点  -是  陛下
- Do you hear me? Now! - Yes, Sire.
也许是我太草率了
Perhaps I have been hasty.
我应该祈求撒慕尔的原谅
I should ask Samuel's forgiveness.
-把撒慕尔带来见我  -他走了  陛下
- Bring Samuel to me. - He's gone, Majesty.
走了
Gone?
撒慕尔
Samuel!
撒乌尔违背了天主的旨意
After Saul's disobedience,
于是天主命令先知撒慕尔
God commands his prophet Samuel...
寻找一位新国王
to find a new king.
年轻人
Young man!
你叫什么名字
What is your name?
达味  先生
David, sir.
我叫达味
My name is David.
我傅油于你  白冷的达味
I anoint you, David of Bethlehem,
在撒乌尔死后
to be the next King of Israel...
继任以色列国王
...once Saul is dead.
父亲  怎么了  告诉我怎么了
Father what's wrong? Tell me what's wrong!
-没事  -这是一场伟大的胜利
- Nothing is wrong. - It was a great victory.
我需要休息  仅此而已
I need rest, that is all.
睡吧  睡吧
Sleep. Sleep...
主啊  宽恕你的仆人吧
Lord, forgive your servant!
后来  达味成了撒乌尔的持戟侍卫
In time, David becomes an attendant in Saul's court.
一位奉侍王室(等待中)的国王
A king in waiting.
培肋舍特人的威胁愈演愈烈
The Philistine threat continues to grow.
现在他们拥有一名新的勇士
Now they have a new champion--
哥肋雅
Goliath.
你们谁敢出来同我作战  以色列人
Will one of you fight me, Israelites!
你们赢了  培肋舍特人就做你们的奴隶
You win, and the Philistines will be your slaves.
我赢了
I win,
你们就做我们的奴隶
and you will be our slaves.
-总得有人应战  -你退下  约纳堂
- Someone must fight him! - Not you, Jonathan.
战胜他的勇士将获万贯家财
The warrior who defeats him will be a rich man.
没有一个以色列人吗
Not one man in Israel?
没有一个"天主的子民"敢出来迎战吗
Not one of 'God's people'?
我来
I'll do it.
达味  你不是士兵  你是牧羊人
David! You're no soldier, you're a shepherd.
是的  牧羊人
Yes, a shepherd.
正如我保护我的羊一样  天主也会保护我
As I protect my sheep, God will protect me.
你们的信心在哪里  你们的天主又在哪里
Where is your faith? Where is your God?
我会杀了他
I will kill him.
带上这个
You'll need this.
没有这个更好
I'll be better without it.
纵使我应走过阴森的幽谷，
Yea though I walk in the valley of the shadow of death,
我不怕凶险，
I fear no evil,
因你与我同在，
for you are with me,
你的牧杖和短棒，
thy rod and staff,
是我安慰的舒畅。
they comfort me.
在我的头上傅油
You anoint my head with oil.
使我的杯爵满溢
My cup overflows.
在我一生的岁月里，
Surely goodness and mercy shall follow me
幸福与慈爱常随不离。
all the days of my life.
看来以色列找到一位勇士了
Israel has found a champion!
别浪费我时间  小毛孩
Don't waste my time, little boy.
你死还太年轻了
You are too young to die.
我要和你战斗
I will fight you!
父亲  他成功了  达味成功了
Father, he did it. David did it!
让我们去抓奴隶吧
Let us make slaves of them!
达味
David!
我的牧羊人英雄
My wolf's in shepherd's clothing!
你挽救了我的王国  牧羊人勇士
You've saved my kingdom, my shepherd warrior!
跟我来  兄弟
Come with me, brother.
达味加入了撒乌尔的军队
David joins Saul's army,
与培肋舍特人对战数十载
and battles the Philistines for decades.
他成了一名勇士
He becomes a warrior,
一位领袖
a leader,
一个英雄
a hero.
撒乌尔 撒乌尔 撒乌尔
Saul! Saul! Saul!
撒乌尔杀敌数千
Saul has killed thousands!
撒乌尔 撒乌尔 撒乌尔
Saul! Saul! Saul!
-你听到了吗  父亲  -我听到了
- You hear that, father? - I hear.
撒乌尔 撒乌尔 撒乌尔
Saul! Saul! Saul!
达味杀敌数万
David has killed tens of thousands!
达味  达味  达味
David! David! David!
他理应得到他们的赞誉
He deserves their praise.
接下来他就该觊觎我的王位了
He'll want my crown next.
我以为你当时摔下马了
I thought you'd fall off your horse.
是摔马了  我摔下来的时候还压死了一个人
I did fall off my own! I killed a man when I landed on him!
一度我看见两个男人站在我面前
At one point there were two men in front of me,
也许是两个女人...
or there were women in front of me...
达味
David!
过来
Come here.
所以...
So...
你又一次成了我们的英雄
...once again, you are our champion.
你杀敌数千
You have killed thousands.
-数万呢  -当然
- Tens of thousands! - Of course.
数万人
Tens of thousands.
我们的人民都非常感激你
Our people are very grateful to you.
天主保佑我们所有人
The Lord blessed us all.
我要奖赏你
I would like to reward you.
我把我的女儿米加耳许配给你
I offer you my daughter, Michal.
我深感荣幸  陛下
I'm very honored, Majesty.
达味  我们现在是兄弟了
David, we're brothers now!
作为回报
In return...
我要一百个培肋舍特人的性命
...one hundred dead Philistines.
你怎么看
What say you?
一百个培肋舍特人  都要由你手刃
One hundred dead Philistines, slain by your own hand.
父亲  他以身犯险的还不够吗
Father...he's risked his life enough, no?
-如果他回不来怎么办  -我会回来的
- What if he doesn't return? - I shall return.
如果天主许可
God willing.
你爱他如亲兄弟一般吧
You love him like a brother, don't you?
是啊
I do.
就像亚伯尔曾经爱戴加音一样
As Abel, no doubt, once loved Cain.
他觊觎我们的王位  你看不出来吗
He wants our crown. Can't you see?
不 他忠于我们
No. He's loyal to us both.
胡说
Nonsense!
给您带了点纪念品  还有这些
A few mementos for you. And these.
从每具尸体上拿回来的战利品
Trophies taken from each of their bodies.
-是一百具尸体吗  -两百具
- From a hundred men? - Two hundred.
天主与我同在
God was with me.
米加耳
Michal!
出去
Get out.
所有人
All of you.
滚出去
Get out!
父亲  是什么魔鬼蒙蔽了你
Father, what demons possess you?
如果不是因为他
If it wasn't for him,
我们都会变成奴隶  你也不会继续当国王
we would all be slaves and you would not be king.
但有了他  你永远不会成为国王
And with him, you never will be!
你父亲  也就是国王  想见达味
Your father, the King, wishes to see David.
不行  他现在...身体不适
He can't. He's...not well.
"身体不适"
'Not well'?
你是说"身体不适"吗
'Not well,' you say?
我们来瞧瞧  来瞧瞧
Well, we shall see. We shall see!
身体不适
'Not well'!
达味
David?
好啊  好啊
Yes, yes...
干得好啊  你帮他逃跑了
Yes... You have helped him escape.
比起你父亲的王位  你更在意自己的后位
You would rather be Queen than see your own father King?
-不  -你背叛了自己的兄长
- No! - You'd betray your own brother!
-父亲  您需要休息  -不
- Father, you need to rest! - No!
连我的亲生孩子都算计我
Even my own children plot against me!
达味
David!
不论你逃到何方  我都饶不了你
Wherever you go, I shall hunt you down!
司祭
Priests!
你们的国王有话要问你们
Your king wishes to speak with you.
-出来  -快出来
- Come here! - Come on, out!
达味曾来过  对不对
David was here, wasn't he?
你们为他提供了庇护
You sheltered him.
这里是圣殿
This is God's house.
我们为所有天主的子民提供庇护
We offer shelter to all his people.
杀了他
Kill him.
我说杀了他
I said kill him!
全部杀掉
Kill all of them.
我虔诚地侍奉你  上主
I have served you faithfully, Lord.
尽我所能  全心全意
As faithfully as a man can,
但如今看来  似乎依然不够
and yet still it seems it is not enough!
天主与我同在
God is with me!
主啊
Lord!
你听见我这忠仆的心声了吗
Do you hear your servant?
陛下
Majesty!
达味
David?
我并未伤害过您  您为何对我穷追不舍
Why do you pursue me when I've done you no harm?
我刚刚本可以杀了您
I could have killed you.
取您性命  易如反掌
Your life was mine to take.
那你为何没有下手
Why didn't you take it then?
主自会惩罚您对我犯下的罪孽
The Lord may revenge the harm you have done to me,
但恶事只出于恶人
but only evildoers do evil deeds,
我却永远不亲手加害于你
so my hand will not touch you. Ever.
可是天主会赏赐你  你将成为国王
And God will reward you, and you will be king!
你才是我的国王
You are my king.
当你戴上我的王冠
And when you have my crown,
你难道会不杀死我的后裔
will you not kill my descendants,
-不会消灭我的名吗  -我不会
- bury my name? - I will not.
-不会吗  -我发誓
- No? - I swear.
不会吗
No?
那你过来
Come, then.
过来
Come.
我们一起回去
We'll go home together.
你当时为何不趁机杀了他
Why did you not kill him when you had the chance?
因为他也是受傅者之一
Because he's one of the anointed.
唯有天主才能决定他的命运
It's up to God to decide his destiny.
父亲
Father!
父亲  父亲
Father! Father!
父亲  培肋舍特军队驻扎在基耳波亚附近的山谷
Father, the Philistine army is in the next valley near Gilboa.
约纳堂  达味就在附近
Jonathan, David is very near.
别再想达味了
Forget about David.
你必须保卫自己的王国  这是你的职责
You must defend your kingdom. That is your duty.
你说得对
You're right.
我们必须备战
We must prepare for battle.
告诉军队  我们要朝基耳波亚进发
Tell the men we leave for Gilboa.
破晓就出发
Tell them we leave at dawn.
约纳堂  别管我了
Jonathan, save yourself!
不  我们要并肩作战
No, we stand together!
父亲  快走  快走
Father, come on! Come on!
约纳堂
Jonathan!
约纳堂  约纳堂
Jonathan! Jonathan!
不  我的儿
No, my son...
不  为什么
No, why?
敬爱的主啊
Dear God...
是否因我罪孽深重
...were my sins so great
所以整个以色列都要受苦受难
that all of Israel must suffer?
培肋舍特人
A crushing victory...
大获全胜
...for the Philistines.
撒乌尔呢
And Saul?
死了
Dead.
你认为天主的受傅者身亡无足轻重吗
You think the death of God's anointed is a trivial thing?
约纳堂呢
What of Jonathan?
被俘了吗
Captured?
杀了他
Get rid of him!
一代枭雄竟这般逝去
How are the mighty fallen.
我们可以回家了
We can go home!
现在人民都指望你来
The people will look to you now
凝聚人心  抵御外敌
to defend them. Unite them!
是时候了
Our time has come.
是的  我的陛下
Yes, my king.
达味王
King David.
达味召集了追随者
David gathers followers.
但想团结以色列百姓  还需要一座都城
But to unite Israel he needs a capital city.
耶路撒冷  我们的新家园
Jerusalem... our new home.
只要想出办法进城就可以了
Now we just need to find a way in.
如何进城
How do we do that?
只有一个法子
There is one way.
等待夜幕降临
We'll wait till nightfall.
现在怎么办
What do we do now?
拿着
Here...
为了以色列
For Israel.
-小心  -拿好武器
- Look out! - To arms!
乌黎雅
Uriah!
以色列
Israel!
耶路撒冷如今成了达味的都城
Jerusalem is now David's city,
这座城是以色列人新的权力中心
a new center of power for the Israelites
也是他们信仰天主的终极象征的家
and a home for the ultimate symbol of their bond with God.
约柜
The Ark of the Covenant!
我的朋友  你妻子太漂亮了
Your wife's far too pretty for you, my friend.
-没错  -陛下
- You're right! - Majesty...
来
Come.
-你不介意吧  乌黎雅  -可我介意
- You don't mind, Uriah? - I mind!
如今天主才真正与我同在了
Now God is truly with me.
陛下
Your Majesty?
先知
Ah, Prophet...
看  这是我献给约柜的圣殿
Look. My temple for the Ark.
也献给主
For the Lord.
这会是世上独一无二的圣殿
The world's never seen anything like it.
主昨晚降临
The Lord came to me last night.
他对我们的成果很满意吧
He's pleased with our work?
主示说  达味家将永远统治以色列
The Lord told me the House of David will rule Israel forever.
-我们深蒙神宠  -你的儿子将继位为王
- We are blessed. - Your son will be king.
你的儿子会建造圣殿
Your son will build the Temple.
-我的圣殿  -主的圣殿
- My temple? - God's temple.
主的圣殿
God's temple.
永恒之国
A kingdom forever.
谢谢你  纳堂
Thank you, Nathan.
陛下
Your Majesty.
如您所要求
As you requested.
退下吧
Leave us.
-巴特舍巴  -陛下
- Bathsheba. - Majesty.
叫我达味吧
David.
可有我丈夫的音讯
Is there news of my husband?
没有
No.
不不  这并非噩耗
No, nothing like that.
虽然远在千里之外
He's safe enough, I believe.
但我相信他应该平安无恙
Although he is far away.
抵御外敌
Fighting the enemy.
但您却没有上战场
But you didn't go?
我不用去
No need,
因为有乌黎雅这样的勇士替我去
not with men like Uriah to do it for me.
我忠于我的丈夫
I am loyal to my husband.
那对你的国王呢
What about your king?
这是不对的
This is wrong.
无人会知晓
No one need know.
巴特舍巴怀孕了
Bathsheba becomes pregnant.
天主选中的王违背了他的诫命
God's chosen king breaks his commandments.
乌黎雅  我的朋友  欢迎
Uriah, my friend. Welcome.
您找我吗  殿下
You sent for me, Majesty.
-战况如何  -挺好的  很顺利
- How's the war going? - Well. Very well.
你的统领官约阿布  他一切都好吗
And your commander, Joab, all is well with him?
都很好
All is well.
-其他士兵呢  -骁勇善战
- Your fellow soldiers? - They fight well.
非常好
Excellent.
你可以明早再来向我详细汇报
You can give me a fuller report in the morning.
我想你现在一定很想和妻子在一起
I'm sure for now you'd rather be with your wife.
-我不能去找我的妻子  -当然可以
- I cannot stay with my wife. - Of course you can.
可我的士兵们还驻扎在野外
While my men are camped in open country?
与敌人激战
Fighting the enemy?
这是一场圣战
This is a holy war.
我怎么可以回家  与妻子共度良宵
How could I go to my home and spend the night with my wife?
所以你这么受人爱戴  乌黎雅
That does you credit, Uriah,
但是说实在的  谁会知道这事
but, man-to-man, who's to know?
我自己
I will know.
正直之士啊
Good man.
让我们开怀畅饮吧
Then let's drink.
上酒
Wine!
达味无法迫使乌黎雅与巴特舍巴同床
David cannot force Uriah to sleep with Bathsheba,
所以他另觅他法  来隐瞒通奸之事
so he finds another way to conceal his adultery.
'"约阿布将军  我命令你派遣乌黎雅
'"Commander Joab, I order you to send Uriah
去战事最激烈的前线
to where the fighting is fiercest
丢下他  令其自生自灭"'
and abandon him there to die."'
我们真是福泽深厚
We've been richly blessed.
你以为可以掩盖自己所做的事吗
You think you can sweep what you've done under the carpet?
你夺走了你最忠诚的仆人乌黎雅的一切
You took everything from your most loyal servant, Uriah.
-你本该敬重他才是  -我确实尊重他
- He deserved your respect. - I did respect him.
是吗  你夺人妻子  又夺其性命
Really? You took his wife, then you took his life...
先知
Prophet!
你以为天主对此一无所知吗
You think God doesn't see everything?
天主已经对我说了
The Lord has spoken to me.
由于你蔑视天主
He will bring disaster on your house
他将让你一家蒙受灾难
for the contempt you have shown the Lord.
-不  -不
- No. - No!
他将带走你的儿子
He will take your son.
我们走着瞧
We shall see.
主啊  我愿奉献一切
Anything, Lord...
请放过我儿吧
Please spare my child.
请告诉我
Tell me...
告诉我该做什么
Tell me what to do.
先是我丈夫  现在又是我的孩子
First my husband, now my son.
我们被诅咒了
We are cursed.
但我是受傅者
But I was anointed.
天主赐福于我
God blessed me.
国王永远不可能高于天主
A king is never above his God.
你本应以他之名治国  而不是为一己私欲
You were supposed to rule in his name, not your own.
我们完了
We're finished.
所有人都会看出  天主已经抛弃了我们
Everyone will see that God has left us.
先知
Prophet?
虽然你意志薄弱  主依然爱你  达味
Even though you are weak, he loves you David.
你在人间建立了天主的国度
You have forged God's nation on earth.
相互慰藉吧
Take comfort in each other.
你们还会有儿子的
You will have another son.
-小心  撒罗满  -让他玩吧
- Be careful, Solomon. - Let him play.
这是圣殿
It's the House of the Lord.
总有一天  他要建造圣殿
One day he'll have to build it.
撒罗满会建造圣殿
Solomon will build god's temple.
但如他父亲一般
But like his father,
他会发现  遵守天主的诫命难于登天
he'll find it impossible to obey God's commandments.
《圣经》下集预告
Next time on The Bible
天主将从巴比伦带来灾难
God is bringing disaster from Babylon!
进攻
We move!
耶路撒冷
Jerusalem!
危难时刻你不向天主传达我们需要帮助吗
Will you not speak for us in our hour of need?
看看外面
Look out there.
为时已晚
You're too late.
战争开始了
It begins.
臣服于拿布高王
Submit to king Nebuchadnezzar.
向他低头
Bow your head.
不管耶路撒冷还剩下什么
And whatever is left of Jerusalem,
随你们处置
help yourselves!
这边走  达尼尔
This way, Daniel.
达尼尔
Daniel!
我们还会回到耶路撒冷吗
Will we ever return to Jerusalem?
耶肋米亚保证过终有一天我们会的
Jeremiah promised that one day we would.
在此之前  我们要怎么办
In the meantime, what do we do?
卑躬屈膝地伺候这个怪物吗
Just bow our heads and serve this monster?
我会让他们低头的
I will make them bow.
给我点火
Bring me fire!
主啊  救救我
Lord, save me!
如果先知所说属实  居鲁士会放了我们
Cyrus will set us free if the prophecy is right.
我不能言而无信
I cannot go back on my word.
我答应给他们信仰自由的权利
I promised them freedom to worship.
那只不过是对他们忠诚的一种考验
It is merely a test of their loyalty.
这是圈套  他们要置我们于死地
It's a trap for all of us. They want us dead.
即将到来的那一位  将用火施洗
There is one to come, who will baptize with fire.
我只是旷野里的声音
I am just the voice in the wilderness,
等待着主的
preparing the way for the...
到来
...Lord.
-我们要做什么  -改变世界
- What are we going to do? - Change the world.
如果你想为天主教的影视字幕出一份福传的力量， 请来Q群180574695【天主的译站】指导交流!